Guide to the Mildred L. Hendrix Papers, 1951 - 1968 UA.29.02.0018
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mildred L. Hendrix papers
1951 - 1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hendrix, Mildred L.
UA.29.02.0018
6 Linear Feet
Mildred Hendrix (1905-1985) was the Chapel Organist and University Organist at Duke University from 1944 to 1967 and Professor of Music from 1944 to 1969. The papers include correspondence, certificates, general subject files, recital materials, photographs, and other programs related to her career as an organist and organ instructor at the University. Major subjects in this collection are music for chapel services, organ instruction and performance, scholarly study of the organ, Duke University Chapel programming, and the Duke University Music Department. English.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Mildred L. Hendrix Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1976, 1983.
Biographical Note
Mildred Little Hendrix was born in Greensboro, N.C. in 1904. She began studying piano and organ at age 7 and received her first degree in Music from Woman's College of the University of North Carolina at Greensboro, N.C. (B.S., 1926). From 1928 to 1929, she took graduate courses in directing and church music at Union Theological Seminary and Brick Presbyterian Church (N.Y.). Also during 1929, Hendrix studied piano at the Philadelphia Conservatory (Pa.). She was a piano soloist and professional accompanist for leading singers, instrumentalists, and conductors during her twelve years in Philadelphia.
Hendrix held positions as organist and choir director at several churches in the Greensboro, North Carolina area. From 1949 to 1952 she spent summers studying at the Organ Institute in Andover, Massachusetts with Ernest White and other organists. From 1953 to 1969 she studied organ with Dr. Arthur Poister at Syracuse University (N.Y.).
In 1944, Hendrix became the Duke University Chapel Organist and the University Organist. At the Chapel, she performed for weddings, funerals, Commencement Recitals and Baccalaureate services, and for all church services. She arranged special performances for Easter and delivered Handel's Messiah every Christmas. She also lectured to groups visiting the Chapel, performed monthly recitals and convocations, and answered all correspondence regarding chapel music. Hendrix worked closely with Rev. James T. Cleland to arrange music for chapel services. Also in 1944, she was also appointed Professor of Music. She taught organ literature, history, and performance, and offered private lessons to students.
In 1963 she was granted a scholarship by the French Government, Division of Cultural Affairs, to study at the International Academy of Music and Art in Nice, France. There she took private lessons with Pierre Cochereau and studied French organ music, instrument history, and music performance. In 1965 she studied in Haarlem, Holland at the International Academy at St. Bavo's Cathedral.
Hendrix was a member of many professional organizations, including the American Guild of Organists, National Guild of Piano Teachers, Pi Kappa Lambda (national honorary music fraternity), the Matinee Music Club of Philadelphia, the Philadelphia Music Club, and the Main Line Music Club. She was a frequent recitalist for various state chapters of the American Guild of Organists.
In fall 1967 she became University Organist Emerita in order to devote more time to teaching in the Music Department. She retired from teaching in 1969, but continued to give recitals around the east coast and teach private lessons until her death in 1985.
Collection Overview
Papers contain personal correspondence, correspondence with organ students concerning practice times and lesson arrangements, records of works played during sermons, clippings and biographical information on organists invited to perform at Duke, photographs, course syllabi, evaluation of potential students, and correspondence and conference material relating to professional organizations. Also contains bulletins and minutes for Music Department faculty meetings (ca. 1960-1967).
Related Material
Photographic Files: Hendrix, Mildred L.
University Archives, Duke University.
News Service Biographical Files: Hendrix, Mildred L.
University Archives, Duke University.
Organ (Musical Instrument) -- United States; Organ music -- 20th century; Organ (Musical Instrument) -- Instruction and study; Organ (Musical Instrument) -- North Carolina -- Durham; Organ (Musical Instrument) -- Performance; Duke University -- Faculty; Hendrix, Mildred L.; Duke University. Chapel; Duke University. Chapel -- Organs; Hendrix, Mildred L.; Duke University. Department of Music
- Correspondence, ca. 1951-1968
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains professional and personal correspondence, including the renovation of the chapel organ in 1966.
  Arrangement note
  Ordered alphabetically and chronologically.
  - Personal Letters, prior to 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Responses, Personal Letters, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - B, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B Responses, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Biggs Registration and Program, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - C, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - C Responses, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, Chapel Organ Renovations (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Dr. James T. Cleland (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - D, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - D Responses, 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - E, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - E Responses, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, Mary Etta Eyler, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - F, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - F Responses, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - G, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - G Responses, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - H, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - H, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - H Responses, 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, Holtkamp, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - I, 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - I Responses, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - J, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - J Responses, 1951-1955 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - K, 1951-1968 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - K Responses, 1951-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - L, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - L Responses, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - M, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - M, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - M Responses, 1951-1959 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Mc, 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Mc Responses, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Miscellaneous, 1951-1968 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, Murtagh Concert Management, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - N, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - N Responses, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - O, 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence, "Out of Town" recitals (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - P, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - P, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - P Responses, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Poem "The Stone", also Stanza 4 for "For the Fallen" (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Q, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - R, 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - R Responses, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - S, 1958-1968 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - S Responses, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - T, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Kimi Tanaka (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Trip, National Academie, Nice, France, Summer 1963 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - V, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - W, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - W, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - W Responses, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence, Wunderlich's Generals (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence, Reverend Howard C. Wilkinson (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - X,Y,Z, 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 62)
- Department of Music, Duke University
  Contains general notes about curriculum, faculty meetings, departmental organization.
  Ordered by date.
  - General notes prior to 1960 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - General notes, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 64-65)
  - Faculty Notes, 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 66-70)
  - Bulletins, 1961-1964, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 71-73)
  - Humanities Council (Box 2, Folder 74)
- Students, 1962-1968.
  Contains correspondence, lesson plans, and job opportunities for organ students of Mildred L. Hendrix.
  - Prospective Organ Students, Fall 1962-Fall 1967 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    RESTRICTED [Student Information]
  - Prospective Organ Students, Spring 1968-Fall 1968 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Course outlines (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Job opportunities for students (Box 3, Folder 78)
- Chapel music, 1953-1968
  Contains materials from organ and choir performances at the Duke University Chapel.
  Ordered by topic.
  - Choir Hymns, ca. 1963-1968 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Choir Presentations (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Preludes and Postludes, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Wedding Services, 1953-1961 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Weekly Organ Music, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 83-84)
- American Guild of Organists, 1954-1965
  Contains correspondence, brochures, student activity reports, and conference planning materials for the 1965 conference held at Duke University.
  - General materials, 1954-1961 (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - General materials, 1960-1968 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Small brochures (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Southeastern Regional Convention (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Students, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Organists, Summer Academy, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Visiting organists (Box 3, Folder 91)
- Recitals, ca. 1962-1968
  Contains correspondence, programs, and notes regarding recitals at Duke University and elsewhere. Also contains planning and correspondence related to the "Quiet Music" nights held on Sundays in Baldwin Auditorium.
  - Recitals of Mildred L. Hendrix
    - Recitals, 1954-1967 (Box 3, Folder 92-96)
    - Recitals not performed, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Baldwin Auditorium, "Quiet Music", ca. 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 98-99)
    - Commencement Recitals, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 100-102)
    - Palm Sunday, Organ and Strings Program, Mildred Hendrix, Organ; Allan H. Bone, Conductor, 22 March 1964 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - Easter Music, 14 April 1968 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Christmas Music, 10 December 1967 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Student Recitals
    - Elender G. Dennis, Senior Organ Recital, 19 November 1961 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Jere T. Farrah, Senior Organ Recital, 16 April 1967 (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Richard B. Fuller, Senior Organ Recital, 21 April 1968 (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - J. Samuel Hammond, Senior Organ Recital, 11 February 1968 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - Catherine Frances Little, Senior Organ Recital, 17 March 1963 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - William K. Stuart, Senior Organ Recital, 10 March 1968 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Advanced, Chamber Music with Organ, 8 May 1964 (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Advanced, 18 April 1967 (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Voice and Organ Recital, Students of Hendrix and Hanks, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Group recital, Methodist Student Center, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Advanced Organ, Baldwin Auditorium, 5 May 1968 (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Recitals of Visiting and Guest Organists
    - Dr. Nelson F. Adams, 13 February 1966 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Arnold Briggs, Jr., 14 February 1965 (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Cochereau, Pierre, 17 April 1966 (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Fernando Germani, 20 November 1966 (cancelled) (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Anton Heiler, 14 October 1962 (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - George R. Hicks, 9 January 1966 (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Robert Burns King, 2 February 1964 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Robert Burns King recording, 2 February 1964 (Audio-reel UA29020018-RR-0001)
    - LaVahn Maesch, 8 November 1964 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Andre Marchel, 5 November 1961 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Marilyn Mason, 26-27 April 1965 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Karel Paukert, 14 November 1965 (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Vincent Persichetti, 6-11 April 1966 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Arthur Poister, 12-13 November 1966 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Preston Rockholt, 5 February 1967 (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Carl E. Stout, 4 February 1962 (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - Carl Weinrich, 3 February 1963 (Box 4, Folder 132)
    - Gillian Weir, 15 October 1967 (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - Gordon Wilson, 19 April 1964 (Box 4, Folder 134)
    - Edward B. Wright, 6 January 1963 (Box 4, Folder 135)
    - Heinz Wunderlich, 10 November 1963 (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - Potential guest organists (Box 4, Folder 137)
- Personal materials.
  Contains resume, family notes and genealogy, and publicity samples from Hendrix and other organists. Publicity samples include performance announcements and general public relations and advertising material created for professional organists to gain employment.
  - Rsum (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - Family Genealogy (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - Publicity samples (Box 4, Folder 140-141)